So we're going to San Francisco today.
所以我们今天要去旧金山。
That's right. I was gonna say—
没错。我本来正想说——
let me know when you're in autonomous mode.
等你切到自动驾驶模式时，跟我说一声。
Then I could be less concerned about my safety.
这样我就不用那么担心自己的安全了。
We have the only stack in the world that has an
我们拥有全世界唯一一套系统架构，
end-to-end— that's right—
它同时具备端到端——没错——
AV stack, that's right,
自驾 AV stack，对，没错，
as well as a traceable, human-engineered one.
同时也保有一套可追溯、由人类工程师打造的系统。
That's right, that's right.
没错，对，就是这样。
Which is very critical because,
这一点非常关键，因为——
you know, for an end-to-end model,
你知道，对端到端模型来说，
it's very difficult to verify
要验证它，
that basically it's always safe, right?
基本上它是否始终安全，是很困难的，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
And the classical stack is developed based on all the
而传统架构则是建立在各种
safety protocols and the process.
安全协议与流程之上。
We know how to ensure safety in software.
我们知道该怎么在软体里确保安全。
Yeah, the thing that's a miracle about Autopilot
对，Autopilot 最神奇的地方就在于——
is that it does amazing things.
它真的能做出很惊人的事。
Yeah, and it drives like a human.
对，而且它开起来真的很像人类。
That's right. Um—
没错。嗯——
Because it's—
因为它——
because it's end-to-end,
因为它是端到端的，
whenever there are things that need to be improved,
只要有任何地方需要改进，
you know that
你就知道，
you can backpropagate that through the whole model,
你可以把它透过整个模型做反向传播，
and you'll improve it for sure.
而且一定能把整体表现一起提升。
Yeah, I think the—
对，我觉得——
the challenge, of course,
当然，真正的挑战在于——
is our AV model, as—
就是我们的 AV 模型，尽管它——
as incredibly smart as it is,
已经聪明到令人难以置信，
and it can reason about the circumstances,
而且还能对各种情境做推理，
we don't know what it can't do.
我们其实并不知道它的能力边界到底在哪里。
That's right, yeah.
没错，是这样。
And so that's—
所以这就是——
that's the challenge, and that's the reason
这就是挑战所在，也正因如此，
why our classical stack is so incredibly important.
我们的传统架构才会显得如此重要。
That's right.
没错。
The thing that's really great about our AV model
我们的 AV 模型最棒的一点，
and our stack is that I don't ever feel
就是搭配我们这整套架构后，我从来不会觉得——
that our AV model would ever be allowed to do
这个 AV 模型会被允许去做出
something
某些——
that is out of distribution.
超出分布范围之外的危险行为。
And the reason for that
而之所以能做到这一点，
is because our classical stack gets involved
就是因为我们的传统架构会介入，
and prevents it from happening, right?
并阻止这种事发生，对吧？
One thing great about our AV model
我们的 AV 模型还有一个很厉害的地方，
is the development speed is just amazing.
那就是开发速度快得惊人。
You know, we have iterated the—
你知道，我们已经迭代到——
right now the version is, I think, twenty-three hundred.
现在的版本，我想大概已经到 2300 了。
We label based on the number of iterations we have,
我们是依照迭代次数来编版本号的，
essentially, and roughly speaking,
基本上，粗略来说，
we have, you know—
我们等于是——
this is roughly over a year, right?
这大概是一年多的成果，对吧？
So we have, on average, less than seven models being
也就是说，平均下来，我们几乎每天都在迭代
iterated every day. Obviously not every—
不到七个模型。当然也不是每一个——
every single one of them makes it to the car.
不是每一个版本最后都会上车。
But because this process is,
但因为整个流程——
you know, just the imaging and trajectory output,
你知道，主要就是影像与轨迹输出，
there's manual steps in between,
中间需要人工介入的步骤，
in the development process,
在整个开发过程里，
they're just minimal.
其实已经被压到非常少了。
That's why we can iterate super fast.
这也就是我们能超高速迭代的原因。
Well— The thing that's really great about end-to-end models
嗯——
is that whenever you're improving the model—
就是每当你在改进模型时——
uh-huh, um—
嗯哼，对——
because it's one giant model that's end-to-end—
因为它就是一个完整的端到端大型模型——
that's right—
没错——
you're not gonna fix one thing and break something else.
你不会修好一个地方，却又把另一个地方弄坏。
The classical models—
但传统模型就不一样了——
because there's so many different modules,
因为里面有太多不同模组，
you fix this one thing,
你修了这一块，
the logic sometimes contradicts with each other.
其他逻辑有时反而彼此冲突。
That's right, yeah.
没错，确实如此。
And so it's so brittle, and you fix one thing,
所以那种系统其实很脆弱，你修一个地方，
you're chasing bugs all around the table,
结果就像到处追著 bug 跑一样，
and it's really hard, you know.
真的非常困难，你知道。
Most control systems which are built the classical way
大多数用传统方式打造的控制系统，
have the same problem.
都有同样的问题。
And it has so many steps.
而且它的步骤实在太多了。
For example, right,
例如说，
today we're actually gonna see a speed bump.
今天我们应该就会碰到减速丘。
You know, based on our model,
你知道，若按照我们的模型来看，
if you think about it,
你想想看，
how do you detect a speed bump and react to it properly?
你要怎么侦测减速丘，并且做出正确反应？
You have to break it into many,
你得把整件事拆成很多、
many steps, from perception and—
很多很多步，从感知开始——
you know, it has to be added in the world model,
你知道，还得放进世界模型里，
in the context fusion,
再放进上下文融合里，
and then basically you have to decide
接著你还得判断，
how early you have to slow down, by how much,
要提前多久减速、要减多少，
you know, and—
你知道，然后——
maybe even based on different speed bumps,
甚至不同型态的减速丘，
we have to do things differently.
还得用不同的处理方式。
But with the end-to-end model, it just—
但在端到端模型里，这些反应几乎就是——
basically just happen, actually.
自然就发生了，真的就是那样。
We didn't even plan for it. It just happened.
我们甚至没有特别规划它，它就是自己做到了。
Yeah, right.
对，没错。
So it's pretty amazing.
所以真的很惊人。
There's so many people building end-to-end models, right?
现在有很多人在做端到端模型，对吧？
But I really think that it's the fusion of the two—
但我真的认为，真正关键的是两者的融合——
yes, that's revolutionary—
对，这才是革命性的——
that gives you
它带来的是——
the superhuman—
那种近乎超人的——
amazing driving capability and the safety.
驾驶能力，以及安全性。
And back to the model, actually, you know,
再回到模型本身，其实你知道，
it does—
它确实——
because it's so big, right?
因为它实在太大了，对吧？
Actually, we do see sometimes,
其实我们有时确实会看到，
you know, when you try to address something,
你知道，当你想修正某个问题时，
it has some, you know—
它可能也会连带让——
something else might get regressed, right?
别的地方出现回退，对吧？
So being able to establish a basically full-blown,
所以，能够建立一整套完整的、
very comprehensive,
非常全面的——
basically a closed-loop evaluation,
也就是所谓的闭环评估机制，
what we call CLE, is super critical.
我们称之为 CLE，这一点极其重要。
This is how we gate our model,
这就是我们拿来把关模型的方法，
to make sure sort of the bad behaviors, yeah,
确保那些不好的行为模式——对——
get filtered out. The thing that I still love, though,
都会被过滤掉。不过我最喜欢的一点还是——
and I think this proves to be true—
而且我觉得这已经被证明是真的——
that even when you have a regression on our AV model,
就是即便你的 AV 模型出现了某种回退，
your classical stack would always guardrail it.
你的传统架构依然会把它守住。
That's right, actually.
没错，确实如此。
That's why, basically,
这也就是为什么，基本上——
our development speed has been so good,
我们的开发速度能一直维持这么快，
because you always have a backup, essentially.
因为你本质上永远都有一个备援系统。
That's right, you know—
没错，你知道——
even if you have minor hiccups—
就算中间出现一些小状况——
that's right, okay—
对，没错——
we will keep retraining, and—
我们也会持续重新训练，然后——
that's right, you know—
没错，你知道——
just keep getting better.
让它一直不断变得更好。
You never have a loss of safety.
你不会失去安全性。
You have a loss of capability,
你顶多是能力暂时下降，
but not a loss of safety, yeah.
但不是安全性下降，这点很重要。
This is gonna be so critical for a robotaxi.
这对 Robotaxi 来说会是极度关键的一环。
When that happens, you know what I'm saying.
等那一天真的来了，你懂我意思吧。
That's right.
没错。
That is the advantage we have,
这正是我们拥有的优势，
as well as we move into L3 and L4.
尤其当我们迈向 L3 和 L4 的时候。
Because we have redundant stack,
因为我们有冗余架构，
even L2++—to scale it, basically—
所以即使从 L2++ 扩展上去，
for L3 and L4, it's—
进到 L3、L4 这件事——
it's just so natural. That's right.
都会变得非常自然。对，没错。
Yeah, that's critical.
对，这真的非常关键。
And then, and then, um—
然后，接下来，嗯——
then there'll be the—
然后还会有——
teleoperations.
远端操作系统。
Right, as a backup system.
对，作为备援系统。
And then, you know, every—
而且你知道，每一个——
every robotaxi—
每一台 Robotaxi——
every robotaxi service should have,
每一个 Robotaxi 服务系统都应该要有，
you know, an air traffic control center.
某种像空中交通管制中心那样的后端控制中心。
And the thing that's really great with our technology
而我们这套技术真正厉害的地方在于，
is that—
就是——
for whatever reason,
不管是因为什么原因，
if the robotaxi were to get stuck—
如果 Robotaxi 卡住了——
uh-huh— all you have to do is give it a couple of waypoints.
嗯哼——
The human-injected waypoint.
由人类手动注入的 waypoint。
That's right, and it should be able to navigate itself
没错，然后它就应该可以自己导航，
right out of it, right?
顺利脱困，对吧？
And because it has a—
而且因为它本身有——
has a safety stack, a backup stack—
有安全架构，也有备援架构——
no safety would ever be jeopardized.
安全性永远不会被牺牲。
That's right. And the other thing our AV model does really,
没错。而且我们的 AV 模型另一个做得非常、
really well is lane-changing capability.
非常好的地方，就是变道能力。
Because classically, when we do a lane change,
因为传统系统在做变道时，
we have to select the gap,
我们得先挑空隙，
we have to do a lot of, basically,
还得做非常多——基本上就是——
rules and heuristics, essentially, right?
各种规则与启发式判断，对吧？
to make sure it's safe. So sometimes it's a bit timid,
为了确保安全。所以有时它会显得有点保守，
essentially, when you have,
尤其当你面前——
you know, cars in the front,
你知道，前面有车，
you have cars in the back,
后面也有车，
basically there's so many rules.
整个判断里充满了太多规则。
That's right, yeah, yeah.
没错，对，就是这样。
And the AV model, basically, in the city,
而 AV 模型在城市道路里，
it's just doing an amazing job in the lane change.
在变道这件事上表现真的很惊人。
It's also very human-like, essentially,
而且整体风格也非常像人类，
and never gives you the feeling of rigidity.
完全不会给你那种很僵硬的感觉。
Well, it—
嗯，因为它——
it imitates the human
它本来就是在模仿人类，
from all the drives that it's been on.
从它看过的大量人类驾驶资料中学习。
Yeah, and then it generalizes from that.
对，然后再把这些经验泛化出去。
That's right, yeah.
没错，对。
You know, the basic concept of deep learning
你知道，深度学习最基本的概念，
is essentially to memorize and generalize.
本质上就是记住，然后再泛化。
Works just fine for a self-driving car.
这套方法用在自驾车上也完全适用。
AI is the single most important technology
AI 是让自动驾驶成为可能的
that made self-driving possible, essentially.
最关键、最重要的一项技术。
But, um—
但是，嗯——
you know, I have been working on this,
你知道，我做这件事已经很久了，
obviously, as you know,
如你所知，这不是一天两天，
for a long time, but the last two—
而是做了很多年。不过最近这两——
three years, my God—
三年，天啊——
you know, yeah—
你知道，真的——
just—
就是——
it's iterating so fast.
它进化迭代得实在太快了。
Yeah.
对。
If you think about particularly the—
如果你仔细去看，尤其是——
the, uh—
那个，嗯——
using an end-to-end model—
采用端到端模型这件事——
that's right, yeah—
没错，对——
was a big deal, yeah.
真的是一个巨大的转折点。
Yeah, basically—
对，基本上——
to some extent, you can think that the—
某种程度上，你可以这样理解——
the whole industry iterated on the first architecture,
整个产业其实在第一代架构上反复打磨了很多年，
which is, you know, um—
那就是，你知道，嗯——
ML-based perception only, right?
一种只靠机器学习做感知的架构，对吧？
For ten years, yeah.
这一路做了十年，对。
And we made lots of progress.
而且我们也确实取得了很多进展。
You know, you know—
你知道，真的——
robotaxi can be done that way.
Robotaxi 确实可以靠那种方式做出来。
Yeah, um—
对，嗯——
But, you know, over the last three years,
但你知道，在过去这三年里，
we're iterating on, you know—
我们一直在往前推进——
we first brought in a world model,
我们先把世界模型引进来，
now we're adding reasoning to it.
现在又把推理能力加进去。
It's really two generations in three years.
等于三年内走完了两代技术演进。
The two fundamental technologies
这两项最根本的技术，
that we're building on top of.
就是我们现在整个系统往上建构的基础。
You know, so—
所以你知道——
so of course,
所以当然，
this end-to-end model architecture is revolutionary.
这种端到端模型架构本身就是革命性的。
But what differentiates us—
但真正让我们与众不同的地方——
uh-huh, um—
嗯哼，对——
and what's gonna make it incredibly fast
以及让我们能够以惊人速度——
for us to deploy to get to Level 3,
部署并推进到 Level 3，
Level 4, and robotaxis—
Level 4，甚至 Robotaxi——
is the fact that we have a classical stack
就是因为我们同时拥有一套传统架构，
as a guardrail, as a safety system.
作为护栏，也作为安全系统。
And because we have a reasoning system—
而且因为我们还有推理系统——
uh-huh—
嗯哼——
so the long tail of experiences that are
所以那些长尾经验，也就是——
probably not in our dataset,
那些很可能根本不在我们资料集里的情况，
can still be decomposed into routine,
仍然可以被拆解成较常见、
type of experiences that are in our dataset.
而且资料集中已有的经验类型。
Yeah, and the car will be able to reason its way through,
对，而车子就能靠推理把它一路处理过去，
you know, how to navigate and how to operate.
知道该怎么走、怎么开、怎么运作。
And so I really think that between these two ideas,
所以我真的认为，这两个概念一结合，
no matter what the reasoning system decides to do or
不管推理系统决定要做什么，
or achieve,
或者打算怎么达成目标，
you always have a safety guardrail behind it.
它背后永远都有一道安全护栏在守著。
And so this iteration system that we have
因此，我们现在这套迭代系统，
is going to move incredibly fast.
接下来会以惊人的速度往前推进。
The reasoning—
推理能力——
and guardrailing—is going to be just revolutionary.
再加上 guardrailing，将会是革命性的组合。
That's right. All of our—
没错。我们所有——
all of our—
我们所有的——
L2++ work—
L2++ 相关工作——
that entire flywheel—
那整个飞轮机制——
you know—
你知道——
collecting data on the road and—
路上持续搜集资料，然后——
that's right, you know—
没错，你知道——
processing the data—
再去处理那些资料——
now we enhance that by
而现在我们又进一步把它强化，
using Neurad and—
透过 Neurad，还有——
and, and—
以及、以及——
and then Cosmos.
还有 Cosmos。
Yeah, good job.
对，干得漂亮。
Good job.
做得很好。
Who knows what a human driver would have done.
谁知道如果是人类驾驶，刚才会怎么处理。
That's pretty good.
这表现相当不错。
Yeah, that entire flywheel is essential.
对，那整个飞轮机制真的至关重要。
Yup, yup.
是啊，完全同意。
As I said, right, on the model side,
就像我刚才说的，在模型这一端，
you know—
你知道——
closed-loop evaluation is so important.
闭环评估真的非常重要。
We are running essentially—
我们现在基本上每天都在跑——
you know, as you know—
你知道，正如你知道的——
two million tests every day.
每天 200 万次测试。
And they are all pixel-based, basically—
而且那些几乎全都是基于像素层级的——
reconstruction of the world.
对世界的重建与模拟。
It's just amazing, basically, how the technology evolves.
技术能演进到这一步，真的非常惊人。
The neural reconstruction we have—
我们现在的神经重建系统——
it's so great, yes.
真的非常出色，对。
That's right. It's so critical.
没错，它极其重要。
And then Cosmos can be introduced as well,
然后还可以再引入 Cosmos，
which we are working on, basically,
这也是我们目前正在做的方向，
to add—
把它加进来——
Cosmos can cover the really rare corner cases,
Cosmos 可以补上那些极端罕见的 corner cases，
and also it can be used to amplify the neural reconstruction.
而且还能拿来强化神经重建系统。
Neural reconstruction is just reconstruction,
神经重建本身只是做重建，
but if you put Cosmos on it,
但如果再把 Cosmos 叠加上去，
it can—
它就可以——
you know, change the—
你知道，去改变——
you know, background,
像是背景，
change the weather, yeah.
改变天气条件，对。
You could augment it, that's right.
你可以把整个情境扩增起来，没错。
Yeah, that's right, exactly, yeah.
对，完全正确，就是这样。
The combination of these technologies
这几项技术的结合，
has really been revolutionary, yeah.
真的已经称得上是革命性的突破了。
There's probably an accident here somewhere.
这附近大概哪里出了事故。
Well, they really ought to get one of our cars.
那他们真的应该买一台我们的车。
Look how beautiful it is.
你看，多漂亮啊。
Here we are driving autonomously into San Francisco.
我们现在正靠自动驾驶一路开进旧金山。
You know, this—
你知道，这个——
this interchange here—
这个交流道——
always gives me a lot of anxiety,
每次都让我很紧张，
because there's so many different highways,
因为这里岔路太多了，
and if you just miss one, you're—
只要错过一个出口，你就——
you're gonna be gone.
整个路线就跑掉了。
You're gonna be late for about forty-five minutes.
然后大概就得晚到四十五分钟。
And so it's so, so terrific to do this autonomously.
所以现在能自动驾驶通过这里，真的太棒了。
So exciting. You said ten cameras—
太令人兴奋了。你刚说有十个摄影机——
uh-huh— five radars?
嗯哼——还有五个雷达？
Five radars, uh-huh.
对，五个雷达，没错。
And how many ultrasonics? Twelve? Twelve ultrasonics?
那超音波感测器有几个？十二个？十二个超音波？
This spot actually can be pretty tricky.
这个路段其实是相当棘手的。
Um, wow.
嗯，哇。
That's nice.
这处理得真不错。
Because basically there's a lot of occlusion,
因为这里其实有很多遮挡，
and when you get on the highway,
而且一上高速之后，
sometimes the car just stops there,
有时前车就直接停在那里，
but you don't see it until basically you turn—
但你往往要到转进去之后，
make this turn, so you have to control your speed.
才真正看到它，所以速度控制就非常重要。
Well, I know this exit very well.
这个出口我非常熟。
I come here all the time.
我常常走这里。
You know,
你知道，
people underestimate how gigantic of an effort it is.
很多人都低估了这背后工程量有多庞大。
You know, you've got—
你知道，你得——
you've got to build a chip.
你得先造出晶片。
Yeah, build a computer.
对，还得打造整台电脑系统。
And even building the computer
而且就连打造这台电脑本身，
that is functionally safe—
都得符合功能安全要求——
so that you've got the chip,
也就是你有了晶片之后，
you've got the system itself,
还得有完整系统本体，
the system has functional safety designed into it.
而且系统本身必须从设计阶段就内建功能安全。
Um, the software stack,
还有软体架构，
the DRIVE OS software—
还有 DRIVE OS 软体——
you know, as in, you know—
你知道，这些也都包含在内——
every component of even the classical stack
就连传统架构中的每一个元件，
need to get to a certain ISO—
都得达到一定的 ISO 等级——
basically. We're gonna make a lane change here.
总之，我们现在要在这里变道了。
Let's see how we do it. See—
来看看它会怎么做。你看——
this is how— yeah, fantastic.
就是这样——对，太棒了。
Very human-like.
真的非常像人类。
Yeah, that's so human-like, right?
对，这真的太像人类了，对吧？
Hard to describe in code.
这种感觉真的很难用程式规则写出来。
That's right, yeah.
没错，就是这样。
The most rule-based
如果是最典型的规则式系统，
would have had the car completely pass us.
它很可能会让那台车整个先开过去。
Yeah, yeah.
对，没错。
And then we make one deliberate—
然后我们再做一次刻意的——
one deliberate move. That's right.
一次刻意动作。没错。
And that's what the one stage—
而那正是某个阶段里——
what we call speed adaptation—
我们所谓的 speed adaptation——
that we try to, you know,
也就是我们会试著去——
speed up or slow down, try to get in the gap,
加速或减速，想办法切入那个空隙，
then start the lateral move.
接著才开始横向移动。
You know.
你知道的。
But that's not how humans do it, obviously.
但人类显然不是这样开车的。
And then, you know,
而且你知道，
our mind—
我们的大脑——
our mind is just mimicking what everybody else is doing.
本来就是在模仿周围其他人都怎么做。
So it's amazing.
所以这真的很神奇。
You know, there's—
你知道，还有一点——
there's of course the AI in the car,
当然，车内本身就有 AI，
but our AI starts with AI, even AI,
但我们的 AI 流程，甚至从用 AI 来处理 AI 开始，
to curate the data that we collect.
用 AI 来整理我们搜集到的资料。
That's right, so that—
没错，这样一来——
Alright, that's an interesting scenario.
好，这个场景很有意思。
Let's see how we handle it.
来看看它会怎么处理。
Oh, we detect from here.
哦，它从这里就已经侦测到了。
Wow, decided to do the lane change.
哇，它决定直接变道。
Uh-huh, that makes a lot of sense, actually.
嗯哼，这其实非常合理。
Because once you cross the street—
因为一旦你穿过前面那个路口——
that's right, once you cross the street—
没错，一旦你过了那条街——
that's not very much distance to stop.
留给你停车反应的距离就不多了。
Is it? We're going straight.
是吗？我们现在是直走。
That's gonna be interesting.
这下有意思了。
So we go—
所以我们现在会——
we'll go past them and then do a lane change back,
先从旁边过去，然后再变回原本的车道，
I think. But it's like the whole—
我猜应该会这样。不过整体来看——
this actually makes sense.
这样的决策其实很合理。
Yeah, see how we do this.
对，看看它怎么做。
Okay, uh-huh.
好，嗯哼。
It's blocked on the right.
右侧已经堵住了。
Yeah, it's already blocked on the right.
对，右边本来就已经被堵住。
And so it anticipated that,
所以它提前预判到了，
and so we moved to the middle lane.
因此先把车移到中间车道。
Yeah, yeah, um—
对，没错，嗯——
Oh, look at this. This is great.
哦，你看这个。这真的很厉害。
This will be tricky.
这一段会很有挑战。
Let's see.
来看看。
We're just about to pass a—
我们现在正要超过一辆——
pass a bus.
要超过一台公车。
Alright, okay, fantastic.
好，太好了，漂亮。
Wow, that's so graceful. Yep.
哇，这个动作太优雅了。对。
It's more peaceful than humans are driving.
它开起来比人类驾驶还更平稳、更从容。
Actually, this is what the media reporters—
其实这正是媒体记者们——
they feel, right?
他们最直接感受到的，对吧？
Safe, for instance.
例如，就是安全感。
Yeah, it's confident.
对，它给人的感觉很有自信。
It's calm, it's safe.
它很冷静，也很安全。
So we have all the AI models that's inside the car,
所以我们车上有一整套 AI 模型，
we have AI models just to curate the data.
我们也另外有 AI 模型专门用来整理资料。
Uh-huh, right.
嗯哼，对。
We don't want a whole bunch of wasted—
我们不希望一大堆资料都浪费掉——
yes, same thing, you know—
对，没错，就是同样道理——
to retest it with the same thing.
不想老是拿同样的情况一直重测。
And so you're looking for—
所以你真正要找的是——
for out-of-distribution things, you're looking for—
你要找的是那些 out-of-distribution 的情况——
that's right, like circumstances that—
没错，也就是那些特殊场景——
that we have the terminology for this,
我们对这件事其实有专门术语，
it's called a functional scenario tree.
它叫做 functional scenario tree。
If you think about it, it's really basically,
你仔细想想，它本质上其实就是——
you know, um—
你知道，嗯——
a bunch of nodes, which are the—
一大堆节点，也就是——
you know, cases we need to cover.
我们必须涵盖的各种情境案例。
And then we have an AI tool to curate data
然后我们再用 AI 工具去整理资料，
to fill in these different nodes.
把这些不同节点所需的资料补齐。
And when we see a new scenario pop up on the road,
而当我们在路上测试时，看到新的情境突然出现，
testing, then we're gonna—
那我们就会——
you know, create one more layer,
你知道，再新增一层，
right, or one more node on this functional scenario tree.
或者说，在这棵功能情境树上再多加一个节点。
Yeah, okay.
对，懂了。
So this is called the functional scenario tree.
所以这整套就叫做 functional scenario tree。
So this with the double-parked car is really great, basically.
所以像现在这种双排停车情境，真的就很有代表性。
You know, it just—
你知道，它就是——
literally we crossed the lane,
它刚才确实短暂跨了一下车道，
but it was perfectly safe to do so.
但整体来说是完全安全的。
That's right, yeah, yeah, yeah.
没错，对，就是这样。
You will see, you know,
你接下来会看到，
some hesitation sometimes,
它有时候还是会稍微犹豫一下，
um—
嗯——
like we're definitely—
像我们现在这套系统，确实——
I would say more conservative than—
我会说它比——
than average driver.
比一般驾驶人更保守。
Because, for example,
因为举例来说，
we'll get that definitely—
我们一定会——
we'll get to at least a moment of full stop
至少做到一次完整停车，
in front of every stop sign,
在每一个 Stop sign 前都会如此，
which is the right thing to do, obviously.
这当然才是正确的做法。
But yeah—
不过，是的——
and so we have the data,
所以我们有资料，
we have AI models
也有 AI 模型，
for your functional scenario trees,
对应 functional scenario tree 的各种节点，
you have AI models for synthetic data generation—
也有 AI 模型专门做合成资料生成——
that's right, maybe—
没错，对——
and we have AI models for neural reconstruction.
还有 AI 模型用来做神经重建。
For sure, right.
当然，没错。
We have— yeah, yeah—
我们有，对，没错——
for, uh—
还有，嗯——
drive logs to reconstruction.
把 drive logs 转成重建资料。
Right, yeah.
对，没错。
When you do engineering, you can keep progressing
当你在做工程时，你之所以能持续往前推进，
and keep adding more capabilities,
不断往系统里加更多能力，
only if the foundation is strong.
前提就是你的底层基础得够强。
It's strong, yes.
没错，基础一定要稳。
You know, when you're—
你知道，当你——
you're taking—
当你正在——
you're investing all these new capabilities,
投入这么多新能力进去的时候，
but, you know,
但你知道，
you can only do so with confidence
你之所以敢放心这么做，
if you know—
前提就是你知道——
there's no regression, right?
系统不会倒退，对吧？
That's really one of the—
而这正是——
the most powerful things about our classical stack.
我们传统架构最强大的地方之一。
It's so safe.
因为它真的非常安全。
Every one of these iterations—
我们每一次迭代——
every single month—
每一个月推出的新版本——
you're quite confident deploying it onto the road.
你都很有信心把它部署到真实道路上。
You know, between the evaluation systems
因为你知道，从评估系统、
and the validation systems,
到验证系统，
and the methodology and the guardrails—
再到方法论与安全护栏——
that's right, it's always safe.
没错，它始终都是安全的。
From here on, our velocity is gonna be so high.
从现在开始，我们的推进速度会非常快。
Yeah, yeah.
对，没错。
So this is a residential area,
所以这里是住宅区，
so in this area—
在这种区域里——
as I said, buses
就像我刚才说的，公车——
are a challenge, and then a lot of random parked cars.
是一大挑战，再加上很多随机停放的车辆。
We call them DPVs, double-parked vehicles.
我们称它们为 DPV，也就是双排停车车辆。
And navigating around them is really,
而且在它们周围进行绕行判断，
really critical, um—
真的是非常、非常关键，嗯——
we got a lot of delivery vans and trucks.
我们常常会遇到很多送货车与卡车。
A lot of them, that's right, exactly.
很多，真的很多。没错，就是这样。
Weekends are better, but weekdays,
周末会好一点，但平日的话，
you know, there's just a lot of them.
你知道，这种车真的到处都是。
And DPV nudging is also, you know, um,
而且面对 DPV 时那种「轻微挪位绕行」的处理，你知道，嗯——
quite difficult.
其实相当困难。
Difficult to get right, but the model, again,
很难做到刚刚好，但模型的优势又在这里——
is learning, you know,
它正在学会——你知道——
what humans do, essentially,
人类本质上会怎么做，
which is great.
这一点非常棒。
But even sometimes humans make mistakes.
但当然，人类有时也会做错。
Uh-huh, you know, um—
嗯哼，你知道，嗯——
so if you make the wrong decision,
所以如果你做了错误判断，
you will end up being in the oncoming lane,
你就可能直接跑到对向车道去，
you know, and yeah—
你知道，然后——
sometimes you get stuck.
有时甚至会把自己卡住。
You know, that's why I think what we are doing
所以这就是为什么我认为我们目前正在做的，
in the current implementation,
在现阶段这个版本里，
is still slightly on the conservative side,
仍然是稍微偏保守一点的策略，
because the cost of making a wrong decision is too high.
因为一旦判断错误，代价实在太高了。
Yeah.
对。
Safety first. Safety first. Exactly.
安全第一，安全第一。完全正确。
It's okay to get stuck, essentially,
本质上，暂时卡住其实是可以接受的，
for an L2++ product, yeah.
尤其对 L2++ 产品来说，是可以接受的。
Even if it's ugly, I think it's okay.
就算看起来不够漂亮，我觉得也没关系。
Yeah, that's right.
对，没错。
If the human's in the car, that's right, right, yeah.
只要车里还有人类驾驶在，对，这样就可以。
That's so great that we got the highest—
最棒的是，我们拿到了最高的——
highest rating in NCAP. I know, yeah.
NCAP 评级最高分。对，我知道，真的很棒。
First time out, it's incredible.
第一次送测就拿到，真的很不可思议。
That's right.
没错。
Because this is the right decision as well.
因为这其实也是正确的决策。
Yeah, because it's oncoming.
对，因为对向有来车。
Exactly, and we're just patiently waiting.
完全没错，所以我们现在就是耐心等待。
And a human might be slightly faster,
人类驾驶也许会稍微快一点点，
but I think we did— I don't think so.
但我觉得我们刚刚其实——我倒不这么认为。
I think I would have done about the same.
我想如果是我，大概也会做出差不多的选择。
Ha ha.
哈哈。
Interesting.
有意思。
And NCAP 2025—
而且 NCAP 2025——
so rigorous—
标准之严格——
and the Euro NCAP,
再加上 Euro NCAP，
the standards are so high.
他们的标准真的非常高。
Yeah.
对。
And we got the highest score.
而我们拿到了最高分。
That's crazy. That's so exciting.
这真的太疯狂了，太令人兴奋了。
I knew we were gonna pass,
我本来就知道我们一定会过，
but to get the highest score is really incredible.
但能拿下最高分，还是让人觉得非常不可思议。
Yeah, that's again many years of hard work.
对，这背后又是很多年的辛苦累积。
Yeah, which is also very important,
对，而且这件事也非常重要，
because all this work—that's our safety guardrail.
因为这一切努力，最终都会成为我们的安全护栏。
That's right, and it will translate into
没错，而且这些成果都会转化成——
L3 and L4 capabilities.
L3 与 L4 的能力基础。
Not bad, not bad.
不错，不错。
Wow, excellent.
哇，太棒了。
That was a good speed-up. Oh yeah.
刚才那一下加速很漂亮。哦，对。
You know—
你知道——
Okay, oh—
好，哦——
good move, very nice.
这个动作很好，非常漂亮。
Yeah, makes sense, yeah.
对，很合理，没错。
So some people just drive right over a little pothole.
有些人遇到小坑洞时，会直接就这样开过去。
I kind of drive around it personally.
但我个人通常会选择绕开它。
Uh-huh, uh-huh.
嗯哼，对。
I think we have to work on it,
我觉得这点我们还得再继续优化，
but that's a very important feature to have.
但这确实是一个非常重要的能力。
Especially on highways, you know.
尤其是在高速公路上，这点特别重要。
Yeah, if you don't avoid a pothole—
对，如果你不去避开坑洞——
but what do our drivers do?
但我们的人类驾驶平常会怎么做？
Our drivers, yeah.
我们的驾驶员吗？对。
Oh, you—
哦，你是说——
you mean just now? It would probably—
你是指刚才那种情况？那大概会——
I wonder what they do. I think they would get around it.
我也很好奇他们会怎么做，我猜他们多半会绕开。
You think so? I don't know.
你觉得会吗？我倒不确定。
Yeah, we can—
对，我们可以——
but we can, I would say, just now,
不过我会说，像刚才那种情况，
hopefully some of them do.
希望其中有些人确实会这么做。
And we can always select those—
而我们也总是可以把那些——
those data, you know,
把那类资料，你知道——
in our fine-tuning step.
在后续微调阶段挑出来使用。
And we can also do reinforcement learning.
而且我们也可以做强化学习。
Yeah, reinforcement learning is—
对，强化学习——
is very effective, really, to have a more capable model.
对打造更有能力的模型来说，真的非常有效。
Right, this is what we are gonna—
对，这正是我们接下来要——
what we are working on for the next generation, right?
这也是我们下一代系统正在做的方向，对吧？
I think reasoning, once it has memory, is very,
我认为一旦推理系统再加上记忆能力，就会变得非常、
very important.
非常重要。
It can get—
它到时就能——
it will need less help from the classical stack.
它对传统安全架构的依赖就会变得更少。
Yeah.
对。
It's so incredible
这真的太不可思议了，
that a billion-parameter model can encode and—
一个十亿参数等级的模型，竟然可以把这些都编码进去
you know, all of this.
你知道，这所有的一切。
But I guess in the end, the question is,
但我想归根究柢，问题其实是——
looking at all these features,
面对这么多输入特征，
what are the salient features
真正重要的关键特征，
it needs to encode?
到底有哪些是必须编码进去的？
It probably is not that much information, right?
也许实际需要的资讯量，并没有想像中那么多，对吧？
Yeah, yeah.
对，没错。
But the salient features—
但那些真正关键的特征——
necessary to predict the trajectory—
也就是做轨迹预测所必需的——
uh-huh, uh-huh—
嗯哼，对——
is probably extremely,
大概其实是非常、
extremely small. That's right.
非常少的。没错。
We see a lot in the world,
我们在现实世界里看到的东西很多，
so we are impressed by the amount of information,
所以我们往往会被那庞大的资讯量震撼到，
but how much of it does it really—
但真正有多少资讯——
does it really—
它到底有多少——
need to contribute to trajectory prediction?
是对轨迹预测真的有必要贡献的？
It's probably very, very small.
答案大概是，非常、非常少。
Very small, yes.
对，非常少。
That's so great, yeah.
这真的太棒了，对。
It started to turn before the car even passed us.
它甚至在那台车还没完全通过前，就先开始转了。
Uh-huh, yeah.
嗯哼，对。
That's what the model does.
这就是模型会做出的反应。
That's what people would do.
这也是一般人会这样做的。
That's what people would do, yes.
对，人类通常就是这样开的。
Channelized cones, Jensen.
Jensen，这种导流锥桶场景也很有代表性。
Hahaha, we set it up all for you.
哈哈哈，我们都帮你安排好了。
That's so great.
这太棒了。
Channelized cones are also amazing with the model,
导流锥桶这种场景，对模型来说也很厉害，
because it's so hard to get it right
因为这种情境本来就很难处理得漂亮，
with the classical stack.
尤其用传统架构来做时更难。
You have to kind of generate lanes from cones, right?
你几乎得从这些锥桶里自己生成出临时车道，对吧？
I would have zero concerns
如果是这种表现，
doing my email all the way through San Francisco.
我一路进旧金山时边处理 email 都不会担心。
You know, how nice is that, right?
你想想，这有多舒服，对吧？
Nice.
漂亮。
Very nice.
真的很棒。
Wow, what a great drive.
哇，这趟自动驾驶真的太精彩了。
The AV stack drives very much like a human,
这套 AV stack 开起来真的非常像人类，
that imitates a human and generalizes incredibly
它先模仿人类，然后再把能力惊人地泛化到
to all these different scenarios.
各种不同场景之中。
And the classical AV stack
而传统 AV stack
gives us the safety guardrails
则提供了我们安全护栏，
that have been fine-tuned and tested,
那些护栏都经过了细致微调与大量测试，
and with all of the engineering rules
再加上所有已经写进去的
that have been put into it,
工程规则，
gives us incredible safety.
就构成了极高等级的安全性。
And so now when we were driving,
所以刚才整段开车过程里，
the two of us were just talking,
我们两个其实只是一路聊天，
enjoying San Francisco, and it was just incredible.
一边欣赏旧金山，一边前进，那感觉真的太不可思议了。
This is the way transportation should be.
这才是未来交通应该有的样子。
That's right— a hundred percent comfortable,
没错——百分之百舒适，
a hundred percent confident,
百分之百安心，
you know, and completely revolutionary.
而且，完全是革命性的改变。